Novak, you've got quite a history here.
诺瓦克 你在这一站有不少故事
I think if I have it right,
如果我没记错
this was your first Masters you ever played
这是你打的第一个大师赛
as far as the main draw.
至少正赛是
And yet the last of the Masters for you
而它又是你最后拿下的一个
to complete your career Golden Masters.
凑齐了生涯金大师
You've had quite a journey.
这一路挺不容易
Took you a while to get
你花了好一阵
over the hump to get the title
才越过那道坎拿到冠军
and then finally you found your way.
最后终于找到了办法
Just talk about your progression
聊聊你这些年
at this particular event over the years
在这一站的变化
and what do you remember about that first
第一次来的时候你记得什么
Yeah, actually thanks for reminding me
对 其实谢谢你提醒我
of that.
这件事
I I wasn't I wasn't aware that this was the
我之前还真不知道 这是
first main draw Masters 1000 that I've
我职业生涯打的第一个
that I've played in my career.
大师赛正赛
So It can be 2005, right?
应该是 2005 年 对吧
Five? Was it?
零五年 是吗
Yeah, okay.
对 好
Yeah, I I do remember now.
我现在想起来了
I played on court one at the time.
当时我是在一号场打的
So grandstand actually.
其实就是看台球场
Yeah, it's been it's been now what 20 21
到现在已经二十
years coming back.
二十一年了
You know,
你知道
the last time I was here I won the title in 23.
上一次来是二三年 我拿了冠军
Had that one of the most epic, you know,
那是最史诗的一场
best of three matches that that I was I
三盘两胜的比赛
was ever part of and you know,
我打过的里面数一数二
great memories.
回忆特别好
It took me a while to to win
我花了好一阵
my first title here.
才拿到这里的第一个冠军
I think I lost four or five finals prior
在那之前我输了四五个决赛
to to winning it for the first time
才第一次赢下来
against Roger.
对手是费德勒
Actually was losing mostly to him
之前那几个决赛
in those finals that I played previously
我基本上都是输给他
and yeah, it was a hard hurdle
对我来说那是一道
for me to overcome really.
很难迈过去的坎
But once I I got the first title it
但第一个冠军一到手
was it kind of felt
那种感觉
as a huge relief in in a in a sense,
某种意义上是巨大的释然
you know, coming back knowing
你知道 再回来的时候
that you won at least once.
至少知道自己赢过一次
So I've had some great support here
我在这里得到过很多支持
from Illinois and Chicago, Ohio,
来自伊利诺伊 芝加哥 俄亥俄
Serbian community that is pretty big.
这边的塞尔维亚人不少
That's what I remember actually
这也是我印象最深的一点
from the 23 finals and 2018 finals.
二三年和一八年那两个决赛
Quite a lot of, you know,
看台上
Serbian flags on the stadium.
有好多塞尔维亚国旗
That was that was really nice.
那真的很棒
And I and I look forward playing
我也很期待
this tournament.
打这一站
As I said that I played last and won in 23
刚说了 我上次打是二三年
and facilities have improved
而这里的设施
so much tremendously.
进步得太多了
Incredible job Ben Navarro
本·纳瓦罗和整个团队
and the rest of the team has done.
干得非常漂亮
Kudos to them.
该给他们点赞
You know, it's it's a it's a huge change.
变化真的太大了
I think it has become one
我觉得对大多数球员来说
of the the favorite Masters events
这儿已经成了
for for most of the players,
最喜欢的大师赛之一
which is which is very nice to see
看到这个我很高兴
and I see why.
也明白为什么
And and you know,
另外
as far as my preparation goes
从我为美网做的准备来说
for New York is is this is great, you know,
这一站太合适了
me being able to participate at least
至少能让我打上
in one tournament, you know, a you know,
一站比赛 而且是
strong tournament.
分量足的一站
Play one or more matches,
打上一场或者更多
hopefully more than one.
希望不止一场
And, you know,
然后
get get myself ready for for New York.
把自己调整到能去纽约的状态
I know I'm just curious what it's like
我很好奇 当纪录片的主角
being a documentary star.
是什么感觉
As someone who obviously
你出门在外
when you go out in public there are a lot
本来就有一大堆镜头
of cameras on you.
对着你
What is it like having them
那把镜头带进
in your more personal spaces?
更私人的空间里呢
Well, it's been a long project,
这个项目做了很久
you know, started in 2017 actually
其实二〇一七年就开始了
and changed many directors and a little bit
换过好几个导演 中间
of a break in Corona a few years.
还因为疫情停了几年
Change of you know, cuts and versions
剪辑版本、概念
and concepts and etc.
也都改过
and, you know, I'm biased
我承认我有偏心
and I I I'm quite subjective.
我很主观
So, it's kind of hard for me to be neutral
所以我很难保持中立
and objectively you know,
也很难客观
give you feedback and talk about you know,
给你什么评价 去谈
what I think of the documentary.
我对这部片子怎么看
Obviously, being very involved in it,
毕竟我深度参与了
and being very emotional about it
情绪上也放得很进去
and sensitive, you know,
很敏感
I leave to other people to really judge.
所以我把评判留给别人
You know, we try to portray
我们试着呈现
at least the some part of the the journey
至少是这段旅程的一部分
or present different things
或者说呈现一些不同的东西
in 90-minute format that is nice,
九十分钟的篇幅 挺好
but you know, in my opinion,
但在我看来
a bit short to to really tell the whole story
要把整个故事讲完还是短了点
and the whole journey.
整段旅程讲不完
But hopefully, that's just the beginning,
但希望这只是个开头
you know, hopefully
希望它
that will trigger more excitement
能勾起更多好奇
and attention and interest to for people
让更多人关注、感兴趣
to to get to know more of my story,
去了解我更多的故事
so be happy to to continue working
所以我很愿意接着做
on something similar in version two
类似的第二部
and three.
第三部
Maybe in different formats, etc.
也许换个形式 之类的
It's been It's been challenging,
过程挺有挑战
but enjoyable as well, you know,
但也挺享受
I I I you know, I like the storytelling a lot,
我很喜欢讲故事这件事
and if you have someone like Jason
而如果搭档是杰森这样的人
who was the director of Last Dance,
《最后一舞》的导演
you know, he's incredible in his craft
他的手艺无可挑剔
and incredible story storyteller,
是了不起的叙事者
and very experienced
在体育纪录片上
in sports documentaries,
又非常有经验
obviously makes it makes your life easier.
那你的活儿就轻松多了
But you know, we had to click,
但我们得先合上拍
we had to find, so to say,
得找到 怎么说呢
a synergy and a common ground
一种默契和共识
of how we want story to be told,
关于这个故事该怎么讲
and from my point of view,
从我的角度
his point of view, and it took some time,
和他的角度 这花了些时间
but you know, I'm happy and relieved
但我很开心 也松了口气
that it's that it's coming out finally
它终于要上线了
in a few days' time, so hopefully,
就这几天 所以
people will like it.
希望大家会喜欢
Post-Wimbledon,
温网之后
you came to New York, World Cup,
你去了纽约 世界杯
stuff like that, and then look back
诸如此类 然后
at you on a national vacation,
又看到你在度假
spend some time in the sun.
晒晒太阳
What is it like, I mean, do you sort
那是什么感觉 我是说
of give yourself a rest and then rev back up
你会先休息 再重新提速吗
and what does that rhythm look like
那个节奏是什么样子
in terms of resting and then going back
先歇下来 再回到
to hard work in the preparation for
高强度的备战里
Yeah.
对
what you're hoping we're looking
你希望的大概是
at maybe a 4-week
四周左右
Well, obviously that has changed,
这个显然已经变了
you know, I mean it it it it does depend
我是说 它得看
on you know family tempo of the life
家里的生活节奏
and things that might surface
还有那些冒出来的事
and come out and need addressing
冒出来 需要处理
and needs my my attention.
需要我去操心
So, I've done quite a bit
所以我在欧洲
of traveling internally in Europe,
内部跑了不少地方
you know, to be able
为的是
to you know be with family members
能陪在家人身边
and do different things the family
做一些这些年
did for me all these years.
家人为我做过的事
Um
嗯
so, it's it's it's it's not really straightforward
所以没那么简单了
as in you know,
不像
as it was for most of my career,
我职业生涯的大部分时间
most of my life where you know,
我人生的大部分时间那样
everything revolves around me.
一切都围着我转
It's not really like that anymore.
现在不是那样了
And and and I and I like
而我喜欢这样
that because I need
因为我也需要
to get get out of that kind of role
从那个角色里走出来
as well and and and be able
也得能走出来
to and what I talked to I talked a little bit
这个我在纪录片里也聊了一点
about that in the documentary,
就在片子里
so you'll see a little bit about that as well.
所以你们也能看到一些
I'm I'm trying to balance the roles
我在努力平衡这些角色
of a professional tennis player
职业网球运动员
and a father and a husband and son
父亲、丈夫、儿子
and brother and I'm trying to be the best I
还有兄弟 我想在每一个
can be in all these different roles.
角色里都做到最好
And you know, it takes takes time
这需要时间
and takes energy and so, I'm
也需要精力 所以
it's it's a work in progress you know,
这是个正在进行的功课
it's something that I've kind
有件事我一直
of underestimated of how you know, big
低估了 那就是
of a of support and sacrifice was from all
身边每一个家人
of the family members around me.
付出的支持和牺牲有多大
You know, in order to for them
为的是让他们
to to allow me to create space
替我腾出那片空间
for 20 plus years to to do my thing.
二十多年 让我去做我的事
And once I'm done with tournaments,
而每次比赛打完
I'm resting, you know, and and it's all
我就休息 关键全在于
about how I rest and how well rested I
我怎么休息、休息得好不好
am once I start preparation.
等到重新开始备战的时候
So, that's that's normal.
这很正常
It's a normal kind of curve in in the cycle
这是职业运动员生涯周期里
of journey of professional individual
正常的一条曲线
professional athlete.
尤其是个人项目
And it's what most of the athletes
大多数运动员
are doing, the younger ones today.
都是这么做的 年轻人也一样
And that's what I've done,
我也一直这么做
but you know, things change
但情况在变
and and I I don't want to have that kind
而我不想让自己
of one-dimensional feeling.
只剩下一个维度
Is there a moment
有没有那么一个时刻
though like like 10 days ago, 2 weeks ago
比如十天前、两周前
where you said, "Okay, now I'm going
你说 好 从现在起
to start getting serious again.
该重新认真起来了
Again, I need this many hours in the gym,
健身房要练够多少小时
this too much time on the tennis court."
球场上要花多少时间
Yeah, obviously there's always
有的 一直都有
a constant communication
持续的沟通
with my professional team.
跟我的专业团队
So, we do have you know,
所以我们
we do plan ahead.
确实会提前规划
It's not like, you know, "Hey guys,
不是那种 嘿 各位
I actually want to play tennis tomorrow,
我明天想打球了
so can you come?" You know,
你们能来吗
it's not really you know, out of the blue.
不是临时起意
It's It's planning and scheduling
是规划、是排期
and calendar and it's you know,
是日历上的事
it's been like that all my life.
我这辈子一直是这么过的
And there's one thing
网球运动员这行
about tennis players,
有一点很确定
you learn to plan ahead.
你会学着提前安排
I don't maybe plan as far as ahead ahead
我现在可能没有排得那么远
as I've done most of my career.
不像生涯大部分时候
In the last couple years,
这两年
it's kind of a little bit less ahead, but still,
排得近了一点 但还是
you know, understanding of, you know,
得清楚
where I am with the state of my body
自己身体处在什么状态
and how much I really need to, you know,
以及我真正需要多少
have you know,
多少时间
work with my physiotherapist hands-on,
跟理疗师一对一地做
prepare my body, start, you know,
把身体准备好 然后开始
with more serious training,
更认真的训练
more structured training,
更有结构的训练
but not the the physical activity
但身体活动这件事
for me never stops.
对我来说从来不停
Even when I'm resting,
就算在休息
I'm doing something.
我也在做点什么
So, it's it's it's my lifestyle.
这就是我的生活方式
It's my choice. It's what I love
是我的选择 也是我热爱的事
to do to stay healthy for my longevity,
为了健康 为了长久
for everything.
为了一切
You know, I don't
你知道 我不
Me too.
我也是
I I you know, I play tennis even
我就算在休息
when I'm resting. I play tennis
也照样打球
with my wife, with my son,
跟太太打 跟儿子打
with my daughter.
跟女儿打
I play with my brothers.
也跟我兄弟们打
We have fun, you know.
我们玩得很开心
Just trying to enjoy life.
就是想好好享受生活